Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 March 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. Woodbridge
    His son convalescent; is preparing for New York with all possible expedition. Can get no settlement nor any money from Holt. Disposition made of Franklin's box of books. Has not received a penny from Benny Mecom nor any reply to his letters.
    Printed in Proc. Mass. IIist. Soc., 2d Ser., XVI, 207.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 April 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Priestley, Joseph. Warrington
    Acknowledging favor of 10th inst., also the parcels of books, from the perusal of which he expects to make valuable additions to his History; this work will come into Franklin's hands in an imperfect condition; hopes he will correct any errors in the French Words, etc. Would be glad of Franklin's opinion on his experiments with vanes; has been wholly employed lately constructing an electrical machine upon a new and improved plan. Mr. Boulanger's remarks on experiments with condensed air. Sends various messages to Mr. Canton. Hopes he can procure him Beccaria's work; sorry that Wilkes' piece is not complete.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 April 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Many contradictory reports circulated until the true account arrived of the Stamp Act being repealed; hopes peace will be restored. Compares number of Presbyterian meeting-houses in America with number of churches belonging to the Church of England; ten times as many of the former; disapproves of this. All trade at a standstill; neither can they pay their debts unless Great Britain allows general free trade. In order to relieve their distress, nearly two hundred poor women employed in spinning flax in the factory. Announces the birth of a son, whom they have taken the liberty to name Franklin Wharton; hopes this proof of their regard will not be disagreeable to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 April 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, William. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging favor of Feb. 25th; fears his letter of the 16th was lost at sea; begs for a copy, if he has it. Keen satisfaction afforded Franklin's friends by the accounts of his examination at the bar of the House of Commons; prominent part played by him in the repeal of the Stamp Act; every merchant writes home as if he alone had accomplished the affair. Sensible letter from the Committee of Merchants in London, but all such advice is frustrated by the people's indiscretion. Is not surprised at Franklin's disapproval of his speech against the Proprietary officers, in answer to the Lodge paper; at such a distance, does not think a right judgment can be formed; all his friends think he acted rightly; Gov. Hutchinson thought the attacks on him beneath notice; the consequence was his house and effects were destroyed and his life endangered. Encloses two applications for favors from the Ministry: one from Col. Croghan, the other from Mr. Geo. Read. Account of a company formed by himself and others to purchase from the French certain lands at the Illinois. Does not want the Chronicle stopped. Betsy sends a cordial thanks for the notice taken of her nephew.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 May 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Parker, James. New york
    Has arrived in New York and accepted the place of Land Waiter; his state of health improved but precarious. Reasons against printing a newspaper himself; his rival in the business would be Mr. Holt who owes him a great sum of money and will probably pay it in time if not interfered with; Holt is aided and abetted by the Sons of Liberty, who carry all before them; everyone afraid to speak against them. Must take the box of goods himself, and will allow Franklin interest from the present day. Benny Mccom promises everything but does not pay a farthing. Acknowledging his favor of Feb. 26, just received.
    Printed in Proc. Mass. Hist. Soc., 2d Ser., XVI, 209.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 May 7; D. attested by Cha[rle]s Moore, Clerk 1p.; The Assembly of Pennsylvania
    That the Agents of the Province be directed to address their business letter to the Committee of Correspondence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 May 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Receipt of the news of the repeal of the Stamp Act. Eminent services of Dr. Franklin acknowledged. Pennsylvania Hospital.
    Printed, with the exception of two unimportant paragraphs, in Works (Sparks, VII, 313).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 May 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Hunt, Isaac. Philadelphia
    Concerning a contest for the best essay, written on "The reciprocal advantages of a perpetual union between Great Britain and her Colonies"; the reward, a medal, was won by Dr. Morgan; the writer was a contestant and considers himself unfairly used by the Trustees of the College; sends both papers to Franklin for judgment; by advice of his friends will publish his essay with a dedication to Franklin, whom he trusts will forgive so great a freedom. On applying for his Master's Degree, an honor he was entitled to, his printer, a poor ignorant man, was summoned and examined as to political pamphlets he (Hunt) had written; later his application was refused, without hearing what he had to say; his ambition greatly checked by this cruel behavior. Praises Franklin's great work in connection with the repeal of the Stamp Act.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 May 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Joyous and satisfactory news of the repeal of the Stamp Act; universal pleasure it diffused. Illumination took place on the evening of the 20th; on the 21st a handsome dinner was provided at the Stadt House and concluded with much decency. There it was agreed that all who (from a patriotic spirit) had procured suits of home-made cloth should give them to the poor, and on the King's birth day appear in new suits of broadcloth made in England. The intention on part of a few to introduce in the Address to the King, Lords and Commons some remarks against the Proprietary Government. A plan conceived by himself and four others to purchase a chain of lots belonging to Springett Penn, which lie between 2d Street and the river Schuylkill; asks Franklin to find out Mr. Penn's price for these and also for Pennsborough Manor. Mentions names of those elected as managers for the work house, which is to be erected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Proceedings in Philadelphia on the repeal of the Stamp Act. The part acted by Franklin in procuring the repeal heartily commended.
    Printed, with the exeception of the concluding six lines, in Works (Sparks, VII, 317).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 June 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Transmitting a letter from the Committee of Correspondence, enclosing an Address from the Assembly to His Majesty; their objections to the Proprietaries not due to personal resentment, but to the unhappiness and injury their government has caused. Great opposition shown to a resolve giving His Majesty assurances of granting aids for the defence of the colonies; reasons for and against; finally passed. Describes the Governor's conduct during the late trouble; evident from Secretary Conway's letter to the Governor, approving of his conduct, "that his honor deceived Mr. Conway by a eulogium on himself which he did not deserve." malevolence of the Chief Justice against Franklin, as shown by public accusation in the House that Franklin was the greatest enemy to the repeal of the Stamp Act. Assembly's grateful sense of the firmness and integrity with which Franklin has served his country. Various considerations which point to the policy and wisdom of changing the Government from Proprietary to Royal. The Assembly, not suspecting that the petitions are rejected and being in debt, are anxious to push them to a conclusion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 June 11; A.L.S. 8p.; Parker, James. New york
    Acknowledging favor of Apr. 6. Unjust treatment he has suffered at Mr. Holts's hands; recounts in detail every transaction he has had with Mr. Holt since their first meeting, at present it stands thus; if Holt will settle his debt to him within three months, well and good; if not, he will arrest him and start to print a rival newspaper. Complaints of the amount he earns as Land-Waiter, of the misfortunes he has had to struggle against, of Mr. Colden, his assistants in the post-office, and of many other things. Bulk of people still dispute authority from home; notwithstanding the late Act of parliament directing every Captain of a vessel to carry all letters to the post-office, the moment a ship comes in, the letters are seized by force and carried to the coffee-house where they are cried out and delivered.
    Printed in Proc. Mass. HIst. Soc., 2d Ser., XVI, p.212.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 June 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Sentiments of Dr. Franklin's friends in Pennsylvania respecting his manner of executing his agency in England. Great honor due Dr. Fothergill for his piece written on the stamp Act.
    Printed in works (Sparks, VII, 318).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 June 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Fine qualities of those worthy men now at the head of public affairs. Great relief caused by Franklin's letter to the Committee of Correspondence, announcing that the petitions will be proceeded on. Infamous and groundless charge preferred against Franklin by the Chief Justice. Regulations in American commerce. Currency. Proprietors determined to give their friends twelve months' notice before surrendering the government.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, VII, 321).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Read, John. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a copy of a letter to reinstate him in the King's service; chance of his being appointed Commissary of the Southwest or Pennsylvania district. Mr. Allen's assertion in the House that Franklin was the great cause of bringing on the Stamp Act. Dr. Smith's remarks relative to an American Bishopric resented by the Presbyterian clergy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 June 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Wythe, George. Virginia
    Begging Franklin to recommend his promotion in the House of Burgesses; promises to be an exception to a quotation from Tacitus regarding ingratitude.
    (Partially mutilated.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 June 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Walker, Hannah. Westbury
    Thanking him for his goodness in freeing her letters; wishes them sent to Boston. Her son happily situated with a good master and a good trade; excellent accounts of him. [Note from Thos. Walker on back of MSS. to the same effect.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 July 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york
    The Assembly of New Jersey broken up; Gov. Franklin and Miss Sally at Newark. Commotion excited by the Stamp Act not yet subsided. Complains of a complication of sickness, infirmities and wrongs; no money from B. Mecom; no business in his shop; expense of living in New York; inadequate pay he receives as Land-Waiter. Reasons for business being so excessively dull throughout the colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 July 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Broughton, Sarah. Philadelphia
    Concerning a feather bed which she sold to Mrs. Franklin, and which that lady refused to pay for; appeals to Franklin for justice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 July 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William
    Indian murders. Resolutions of Parliament relative to commerce. Assembly troubles in Virginia and Massachusetts. His victory over the New Jersey Assembly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 July 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Parker, James. New york
    Acknowledging favor of May 9th; delays printing a newspaper in hopes of getting a settlement with Holt. Reasons for the dull and gloomy outlook in New York, and the high prices for everything. Mr. Hall's accounts. Electrical machine not yet delivered. Goes over again all his crosses and hardships; would be glad of a better allowance in the post-office. His types all worn out; asks Franklin to aid him in getting some new ones. Thinks Mr. Colden rather too much of a gentleman for the due execution of the post-office duties. His son stronger.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 Aug. 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Balfour, James. Virginia, Little England
    Acknowledging Franklin's kindness to him while in London; embraces every opportunity to set forth publicly Franklin's eminent services to America; his great qualities certain to confound his enemies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 August 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Brown, Ephraim. Philadelphia
    Having previously announced the death of Franklin's worthy brother [Peter], must now inform him of the death of his widow; nothing to hinder him now from embracing Franklin's generous offer to put him into a printing office in London. Is going to resign the post-office to Mr. Thos. Foxcroft; intends working with Mr. Hall until he hears from Franklin. Mrs. Franklin having left no will, her promise to leave him the little sho possessed is of no value.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 August 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york
    His son's sickness and his own ill health. Holt's promise to pay him on the first of next month not to be depended on. Every farthing of his allowance goes in the necessaries of life; wishes his salary as Comptroller could be made more nearly adequate to his services. Very little stationery sold in his shop; too much competition. Benny Mecom generous in promises but never in payments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 August 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Philadelphia
    Introducing Dr. Jonathan Potts, son of Franklin's friend, John Potts. Esq., who goes to Europe to continue his studies in medicine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 August 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Tissington, Anthony. Alfreton
    Trust Franklin's German tour was pleasing to himself and useful to Sir J. Pringle. Account of his wife's recent illness. Hopes he has received his paper on Mineral Customs. Desires a visit from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 August; A.L.S. 1p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Introducing Jonathan Potts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 September 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Sturgeon, William. Philadelphia
    His health so poor that he has been obliged to retire into the country. The mission of Burlington being left vacant by the death of Mr. Campbell, asks Franklin to intercede with the Society on his behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 September 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Parker, James. New york
    Thinks Holt a villain; is now applying to a lawyer to suc him. Both his boys sick. Times unfavorable for printing a newspaper. Hot summer; sickness prevalent. Engaged in printing an almanac. Complains of his salary as Land-Waiter; no chance of promotion. Expense of living in New York; doctor's bills,etc. Temper of Benny Mecom and Mr. Holt as compared with his own. Reported death of his nephew at Cape Fear. Inconsistency in being afflicted with gout and poverty. Troubles of his friend, Hughes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 September 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Penn, Ann. Dublin
    Writes instead of her son, Springett, who has been very ill, but is now recuperating in the country. Hopes Franklin has recovered from his late fatigue and indisposition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 September 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Walker, Hannah. Westbury
    Acknowledging favor of 13th [name of month torn out]. Sorry to hear of his loss; promises to be frugal and industrious. Intense gratitude for past and present favors. Begging his acceptance of some small offerings for himself and Mrs. Stevenson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 September 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Priestley, Joseph. Warrington
    Relating to a History of Electricity, which he is writing. Curious experiments with an electrified chain.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 273).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766; A.L.S. 2p.; Kent, Benjamin. Boston
    A new cure for the gout. Would like to see Dr. Franklin commissioned as Governor of Massachusetts Bay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Thomas. Lutterworth
    Expressing deep appreciation of Franklin's kindness to himself and daughter; overjoyed to hear of the latter's convalescence; thanks Mrs. Stevenson for her extraordinary goodness to her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Parker, James. New york
    No settlement with Holt. Obstacles in the way of publishing a newspaper. Had the wettest summer ever remembered; universal sickness and distress, especially in his own family; his expenses more than his income. Asks once more if his allowance in the post-office cannot be enlarged a little. "A little more struggling through life will probably carry him out of it."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Potts, Jonathan. Liverpool
    Letters Franklin will receive introducing the writer and his friend, Mr. Benjamin Rush; requesting him to write to any gentlemen in Edinburgh in their favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Ronayne, Thomas. Cork Ireland
    Acknowledging favor of April 20th, with his book on Whirlwinds, Waterspouts, etc. Describes various electrical experiments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Rush, Benjamin. Liverpool
    Has procured some letters of introduction from Franklin's friends in Pennsylvania, whose import, he hopes, will gain Franklin's favor for him; begs him to write to such of his friends in Edinburgh on behalf of his friend Mr. Potts and himself as will be most useful to them in the prosecution of their studies. Franklin's merit and learning held by him in high esteem.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york
    No prospect of bringing Holt to settlement; has therefore started a newspaper; small number of subscribers. Continual sickness and distress in his family. Expense of living. Question of having his salary increased. His accounts with Holt and B. Mecom. Electrical machine in his store-house; Mr. Hughes will not take it until he can pay for it. Lewis Jones has left his service to become a flogger and drummer in the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Galloway, Joseph. Philadelphia
    News of a change of Ministry received with real concern; fears that it will prevent a change of Government; asks Franklin's opinion. Chief Justice declared publicly in the House that Secretary Conway had rebuked Franklin when he applied for a hearing on the petitions, and assured him that they were laid aside by His Majesty never to be resumed; does not believe this but would like the power to deny it. Uneasy about their poor friend H., who, owing to his having written many indiscreet things, is much disliked by both parties; wishes means could be found to raise him above the malice of his unrelenting enemies. The last election a complete victory; new mode of electing approved by both parties; prevents perjury and fraud. Joseph Wharton sends kindly remembrances.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 October 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Dick, Sir Alexander. Prestonfield
    Acknowledging his favor of 11th inst. Expressing gratitude on behalf of his friend Mr. Swinton for Franklin's great kindness to him. Lord Kames's admiration for Franklin; great accession to his estate by the death of Lady Kames.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Monchy, F W de. Rotterdam
    Acknowledging his favor of the 23d ult. Questions concerning a fire-engine. Compliments to Sir John Pringle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging his favor of the 13th Sept. Will give him particular pleasure to receive the "Police of Amsterdam"; orderly government of that city. Good results expected from the erection of the work-house. Glad of Franklin's approval of the Illinois scheme. Will receive from Galloway the Resolves of the Assembly and their instructions relative to the change of Government. Informed that Sir William Johnson has had a treaty with Pontiac and a great number of southern Indians at Oswego, and has settled matters to their satisfaction.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york
    Acknowledging favor of Sept. 1st. Nothing has prospered with him. Continual sickness in his family. No news of his son since he went to sea in a small schooner ten weeks earlier bound for North Carolina. Poor success he has met with in printing his almanac and his newspaper. Lewis Jones has repented and returned to him. H.Hughes is a Son of Liberty and is greatly displeased with his brother and Franklin, whom he will believe favors the Stamp Act. Holt grown popular by his appearance against the Act.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1766?] November 13; 4p.; Franklin, William
    The office of agent for the province of New Jersey. Appointment of Mr. Wilmot under a misapprehension; his intended removal. Goddard's printing business in Philadelphia in opposition to Hall. Hall unfriendly to Franklin, Goddard to publish a newspaper. Has rented Franklin's press and the Market street house to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Gale, Benjamin. Killingworth
    Describes the case of a patient of his, who is a sufferer from dropsy; saw in a magazine an account of the effects of the meadow saffron by Dr. [Wm.] Stark; would like Franklin to ask Dr. Pringle's opinion of this drug, and if it has been successfully tried, to send him a sufficient quantity. Begs Franklin to correct a misstatement concerning his experiments in inoculation, made by Dr. Huxham in the Gentlemen's Magazine for August.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, James. New york
    Enclosing two or three of his newspapers; small number of subscribers. Heard from his son, whom he had given up for lost; was detained by violent gales. Sickness in his family continues.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Pownall, Thomas. Westrop
    Scarcely forgiven by Lady Fawkener for not bringing him down to this place. Has promised her that he will come at Christmas.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 December 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Potts, Jonathan. Edinburgh
    Fears that he did not receive a former application for letters to friends of his in Edinburgh in favor of Mr. Benjamin Rush and himself; since their arrival, finding that such letters would be of infinite service, he takes the liberty to repeat the request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Received the enclosed letter from Dr. Priestly concerning a list of books on electricity, which he is in a hurry for. Regrets not meeting Franklin at St. Paul's Coffe-house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 December 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Parker, James. New york
    Thanking Franklin for the extra allowance of B#20 per annum. Continues to print a newspaper without the least appearance of success; compares his failures with Holt's successes; has had a warrant out for his arrest for three months but he keeps close and cannot be taken; Mecom's and Holt's debts to him. His son returned, having spent all his money, and in debt for his passage home. His type all worn out; asks Franklin for new ones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 December 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Tunnicliff, John. Langley Lodge, near Derby
    Describing the Kind of plantation he would like; if Franklin knows of such a one in Pennsylvania or New Jersey would be glad to hear of it. Begging his acceptance of a woodcock and a partridge.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1766 December 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Parker, James. New york